A Finding Aid to the Julian Stanczak Papers, 1938-2002, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Julian Stanczak papers
1938-2002
Archives of American Art
Stanczak, Julian, 1928-2017
AAA.stanjuli
Archival Resource Key
0.4 Linear feet
The Julian Stanczak papers measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1938 to 2002. The collection documents Stanczak's life through a series of microfilmed scrapbooks containing printed materials, letters, photographs, and writings. Also included are professional material made up of video recordings documenting Stanczak's career and transcripts for a series of interviews conducted by Neil K. Rector with Stanczak.
Biographical / Historical
Julian Stanczak (1928-2017) was a Polish-born American artist. He was born in Poland in 1928, and he emigrated to the United States in 1950, settling in the Cleveland, Ohio area. Th Op Art movement was named for his first major exhibition in 1964. Stanczak also taught at the Art Academy of Cincinnati and the Cleveland Institute of Art. Stanczak died in 2017.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into 2 series.
Series 1: Professional Activity Files, 2000-2002 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Scrapbooks, 1938-1974 (microfilm reel 871)
Scope and Contents
The Julian Stanczak papers measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1938 to 2002. The collection documents Stanczak's life through a series of microfilmed scrapbooks containing printed materials, letters, photographs, and writings. Also included are professional material made up of video recordings documenting Stanczak's career and transcripts for a series of interviews conducted by Neil K. Rector with Stanczak.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Lent for microfilming 1974 by Julian Stanczak. Videos and transcripts were donated by Stanczak in 2007.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reel 871 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Existence and Location of Originals
Scrapbooks returned to donor after being microfilmed.
Optical art; Scrapbooks; Interviews; Video recordings; Illustrators -- Ohio -- Seven Hills; Painters -- Ohio -- Seven Hills; Rector, Neil K.
- Professional Activity Files, 2000-2002; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Material consists of the transcripts of the "Communicating in A Different Way" interviews Neil K. Rector conducted with Stanczak. Also included are a four part video series associated with "Communicating in A Different Way" interviews and two videos on the works of Stanczak.
  - "Communicating in A Different Way", 2000 June 22-24; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "A Color Odyssey", circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 1)
    Tape 1 of a video series associated with "Communicating in A Different Way" interviews
  - "Into the Eye's Mind, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 2, Item 2)
    Tape 2 of a video series associated with "Communicating in A Different Way" interviews
  - "A Vision in Full Color", circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 1)
    Tape 3 of a video series associated with "Communicating in A Different Way" interviews
  - "From Visualization to Realization", circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 2)
    Tape 4 of a video series associated with "Communicating in A Different Way" interviews
  - "The Perceptive Eye", 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 1)
  - "Symphony in Color", 2002; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1938-1974; Series 2; Archival Resource Key
  Three Scrapbooks loaned by Stanczak to the archives for microfilming. Materials present include correspondence, printed material, some writings by Stanczak, photographs,and biographical material such as awards. Also included is Stanczak's thesis presented at Yale University, "Spacial Relationships On the Two Dimensional Surface."
  - Scrapbooks, 1938-1974; Archival Resource Key; 3 Scrapbooks (Reel 0871)